we you start you start by being mindful
of the experience as a whole that's
already that's all read you something try that's
that's all read you something try that's
always something you try to put in a
foreground so by for example you're
mindful of being seated on a mountaintop
answering the question that is your
present experience so that is always the
necessary starting point not to be
absorbed with one particular sensation
or feeling or something like that but
really to see what your general
situation is and you initially of course
you won't be able to do it perfectly
which means you're gonna be making an
object out of that general awareness but
this is somehow sort of something you
have to you have to deal with gradually
through through trial and error because
you know you don't want to be making an
object out of your general experience
what you want to do is discern the
general experience that's already there
even when you don't attend it so the
common tendency is just when you look at
something you put it all into the
foreground what we often say here so you
mean people try to try to attend to be
mindful of the experience as a whole in
this general manner they still try to
cram that into the foreground and in a
way you determine what the foreground is
by way of attending it so it's something
you look at directly that's foreground
for you at that time that foreground has
a reason that foreground is enduring and
that's just the structural thing that's
just how attention works but within that
set up you want to start to develop a
peripheral vision in regard to that
whichever foreground it is without
making that peripheral vision a new
foreground with by overly attending it
that's why that's why the Buddha would
refer to that as yoni Samana Saqqara
so if man a cigar your attention pali
word for attention it's what's in the
foreground yoni Samana Sakura is death
which is aware of the background while
this foreground is
Yanis amines womb so if you have a thing
in front of you you're aware of its
background as in you're aware of the
womb where it came from so to speak of
course so the point is to learn how to
attend that's what got translated as
proper attention by learning how to
attend you can learn how not to over
attend and keep just seeing foreground
and become completely unaware of the
simultaneously peripherally present
background integral to any experience
that's where the body postures are often
listed as anchors and reference points
for mindfulness because they always go
into the background so while I'm seated
I'm talking and I'm actively attending
certain things that I'm doing I'm
writing and talking I'm looking or
whatever while I'm seated so my
background is seated basically it's it's
it's rooted in a body posture and that's
where the mindfulness and Samadhi that
comes out of it it's it's translated as
a reference point or anchoring because
that is what background is even when you
like like on a ship if you throw an
anchor into the into the water it sinks
down it disappears from the vision it
goes into the background and it holds
you they're saying reference you're not
constantly keeping reference in front of
you you have it in the background and
you refer to it when necessary so but
the problem with with this it's it's
something that needs to be developed
people can't just figure it out because
you know for example now you hear about
the background you hear about the
mindfulness in regard to it and then you
just turn to look at it in the same
manner you turn to look at other things
to attend them which means what you're
going to see it's going to be that
foreground because as I said it's
determined by the way you attend it that
that item is what foreground is which
means anything that's peripheral to that
which you're not attending that's the
background so you want to develop that
indirect vision so to speak whereby
without moving your eyes again
metaphorically speaking without moving
your attention to the background you
start to discern it as simultaneously
present their own at the
level so in this sense why do you
mindful if you're talking that's what
that's what the problem is when people
get absorbed when they think the
practice of Samadhi is absorption in one
particular point so not just that you
are focusing on the foreground then
you're focusing twice as hard on that
foreground hoping to catch a perfect
perception a perfect moment to see it
and so on which means you twice as much
unaware of the of the background which
is the the foundation of the mindfulness
again the foundation reference anchoring
whatever going to call it means being
aware of something without actively
having to think about it that's why that
mindfulness automatically if done
correctly results in knowledge because
that's the definition of knowledge
knowing something without actively
having to think about it all the time
the knowledge is there when there is
need for it you know you understand so
that's the whole point that's why this
mindfulness results in Samadhi which
then results in wisdom it's developing
along the same lines so the trick is to
keep practicing and repetitively in a
sense of learning how to attend things
and then become aware of the background
in regard to what you're attending
without needing to attend to that
directly and that can be done through
mindfulness of feelings mindfulness of
thoughts marvelous of intentions that's
why I often talk about taking up
responsibility for example if you take
up responsibility no matter what
particular engagement of your attention
is with a particular task the background
is you are responsible for it it's your
choice it's your karma it's the thing
you chose to do which means it's being
felt on that responsible over which
means you're automatically mindful
through accepting responsibility you're
already doing the correct way of
establishing a mindfulness in regard to
that background so that's the difference
that they cannot be seen overnight or in
one go but it is possible just through
through through sheer repetition and
commitment but also through this
understanding of what you how you're
supposed to do it you're not expecting
like to attend the
big thing a perfect meditation object or
something they would then do the work
for you I've then revealed the truth no
you do the work but knowing what the
work is that's where the Buddha would
say in the suit does he goes and listens
to wise men then he ponders of what he
heard and he measures the task I think
he knows exactly that's a precursor
towards right understanding knowing
exactly what you need to understand and
that's how you can make the effort to
understand it so the practice of
mindfulness or the practice of of
composure which is the price of Samadhi
you need to learn how to see things
without directly looking at them which
means you need to develop that in direct
recognition indirect discernment or
simply mindfulness that's what
mindfulness is mindfulness and
effectiveness it's keeping that
background perspective in regard to what
you're doing now without trying to over
attend what you're doing now all without
trying to overly attend that background
perspective or losing the sight of it as
well so that's why the best way to start
this is just well that's why the best
way to start is is to start this is to
to start by being mindful just just in
the most generic sense of your
experience as a whole don't try to
analyze it or try to pin it down into
sensations or perceptions whatever you
might be experiencing in your body just
just be mindful know the fact that you I
don't know seated on the chair in a
little cave and answering questions for
example let's let's start with the most
obvious one or from your from your point
of view sit seated on the chair
listening to the answer so that's your
situation within that there are many
ways you can indirectly establish their
perspective properly so you can be
mindful of of your body posture you can
be mindful of the general feeling of the
mood for example that's where moods
often will have a sway over people
because that's something that's not
something you can directly think or
perceive your general feeling yet it
clouds everything any kind of pushes you
in directions or for craving for this or
avoiding that it affects your behavior
but if you learn how to be mindful the
mood becomes that impersonal like a whether
becomes that impersonal like a whether
that just comes and goes and that's your
reference point in regard to particular
things you're doing of course that
doesn't mean you can do whatever you
want particularly because they diverge
to the sealer there is sense restraint a
moderation in eating in and senses
avoiding over sensing that's necessary
because if you're engaging with that
it's impossible to develop the extent of
that yawn is so monastic our attention
they will develop that scope to see the
background simultaneously present with
whatever foreground you are engaged with
and that's why that that correct
practice of that foreground and
background so to speak is no other than
then understanding the principle but
it's some part as well that's what I
mean if you do mindfulness correctly
wisdom is is is inevitable and so you
don't have to you don't have to wait for
a certain revelations or something like
that basically you develop it by
understanding what you're supposed to
develop when you need to develop and so
with the simultaneously present
background and simultaneously attended
foreground those are two things that are
in separate and why because foreground
determines what it's not foreground
what's that peripheral things by
choosing to look at this means
everything else you're not looking at it
it's that peripheral crudely put and an
equally the possibility of attending one
particular thing it's only because it
determined by the peripheral by the all
other possibilities that are not
attended at a time so these two things
are inseparable and it is it's like you
attend this means something else is
indirect to that attention something
else else is the opposite direction of
where the attention came from and see
honest ramana Sakura and so that's what
I mean and that's that's that's a
particular principle that says with this
this is with the rising of this this
arises with manifestation of this is
manifested no matter how he translated
the point is you get understand that the
sense of self that the self centeredness
of normal human experience the point of
action the point of choice completely
redundant is just possibilities and
attention possibilities and intentions that are
possibilities and intentions that are
being attended so things that you attend
are are a reason because they were given
as an option to be attended to which
means then the background of that
determines what your attending
determines your the types of your
intentions as well of course then your
intentions up dragging the background
for so if your intentions are for
example focus on sensuality or ill-will
all the time well those are going to
become your predominant possibilities of
that background but if you become aware
you see that the whole thing works
background foreground attentions
possibilities actions chatting our
choice and so on completely
[Music] automatically for the lack of better
automatically for the lack of better
word they don't need any sense of self
and they don't need the agent of me and
mine too in order to be governed that's
why our aunt still continues to talk
walk sit decide choose prefer all of
those things